Jalil Ogunniyi

💌 ja.ogunniyi@gmail.com 🎧 github.com/darthrighteous 👂 Lagos, Nigeria **\(+(234) 809 948 0333**

in linkedin.com/in/jaliloa

Senior software engineer specializing in Ruby on Rails, Next.js, and SQL, with full-stack expertise in building and scaling web applications. Experienced leading teams to build and maintain high throughput systems - armed with lots of technical war stories.

EXPERIENCE

Aster BI (Accounting) Full-Stack Software Engineer

Jan 2024 - Present

- Built and launched a bookkeeping product, www.asterbi.com, from scratch using Next.js(frontend) and Ruby on Rails(backend). Scaled to 800+ customers.
- Processed 4,000+ invoices in the first year, along with support for expense tracking, business reports, taxes, and role-based access control.
- Designed and implemented a robust payment processing system capable of 100k daily payments, supporting retries, fallbacks, fees, settlements, and reconciliation. Facilitated integrations with 2 payment partners.
- Led product direction, conducting 40+ customer clarity calls, defining requirements and executing implementation.
- Delivered 5+ key financial tools, including automated VAT and WHT forms, on-demand financial statements.
- Integrated real-time monitoring tools and self-hosted BI dashboards for tracking 30+ key performance metrics.
- Built a subscription management system with feature-based plans, trial periods, renewals and prorated payments.

Branch International (Lending & Payments)

Remote

Senior Software Engineer Software Engineer

Oct 2021 - Dec 2023 Apr 2019 - Oct 2021

- Led the development and launch of debit cards, handling \$80k in weekly transactions. Built the card application Android UI(Kotlin), and admin tools(using Rails) for card production, delivery, disputes, and reconciliation.
- Integrated NIBSS payments into Ruby on Rails monolith, saving \$40k/week in bank transfer fees.
- Built a server driven-ui system across Rails and Android, enabling optimizations in onboarding and payment flows for all product teams.
- Established app monitoring best practices, reducing crash/ANR by 45% over 12 weeks and boosting play store rankings.
- Led technical team to build and maintain a wallet system handling 100k+ weekly transactions across Nigeria and Kenya; increasing monthly active users by 25% in the first 12 weeks.
- Integrated GTBank payments using Ruby on Rails, processing \$70k/week in cash payments, supporting loan financing strategy.

Andela (Talent) Software Engineer

Oct 2018 - April 2021

- Enhanced a talent management app with surveys and interactive tutorials using Ruby on Rails and Javascript, increasing NPS from 5 to 6 in 12 weeks.
- Mentored 8 junior engineers in technical and product development skill through the Stackup program.

PROJECTS

- Active Record ObscuredID (Ruby) Open source(360+ downloads) library for generating exposable IDs for Rails models.
- Paystack Gateway (Ruby) Open source(170+ downloads) library providing modules binding to the official paystack API.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Technologies & Frameworks

Rails, Next.js, React, Android

Languages

Ruby, Javascript, Typescript, Kotlin, Java

Datastores

PostgreSQL, Redis, SQLite, Snowflake, MySQL, Redshift

Devops & Cloud

AWS(EC2, S3, RDS, Lambda), CircleCl, Heroku, Docker, GitHub Actions

Monitoring & Analytics

Datadog, New Relic, Metabase, Papertrail, Sisense, Google Analytics

Other skills & Tools

API Design(REST, GraphQL), System & Data model Design, Performance, Modular/Microservices Architecture, TDD, Git

EDUCATION

University of Birmingham, UK. BEng, Electronics & Electrical Engineering

10/2013 - 07/2016

Built a C++ application which modelled the particle filtering algorithm for SLAM(simultaneous localization and mapping).